Preliminary Guide to the Lionel Barrow Papers, 1940-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Lionel Barrow papers 1940-2008
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barrow, Lionel C., 1926-2009.
38.1 linear feet Extent: 28,575 Items
Dean of Howard University School of Communications, 1975-1985; founder of the Minorities and Communications Division of the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication. Collection includes materials from Lionel Barrow's advertising career, his teaching and tenure at Howard University, and his involvement in the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC). The earliest materials include student work from Barrow's youth and his studies at Morehouse College, as well as materials from his service in the 24th Infantry Regiment during the Korean War. Another significant portion of the collection is Barrow's newspaper clippings and subject files, dating largely from the 1960s-2000s. His research on an unfinished book about the Freedom's Journal is also a large component of the collection. Also included are numerous photographs, some dating as early as the 1950s, but the bulk of which date 1982-2000s. These include family vacations and events, as well as professional events with AEJMC, the National Association of Black Journalists, and other conferences and organizations. Another notable component of the collection is the section of materials from Barrow's mother, Wilhelmina Barrow, who served as an American Red Cross Girl in Europe during World War II and the post-war period. Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
RL.00084
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Lionel Barrow Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2010.
Biographical Note
Lionel C. Barrow, Jr., was born in New York in 1926 to Lionel C. and Wilhelmina Barrow. He attended Morehouse College and graduated with Martin Luther King in 1948. He also served in the U.S. Army from 1945 to 1947, and from 1950 to 1953.
Barrow attended the School of Journalism at the University of Wisconsin, earning his master's degree in 1958 and a doctorate in mass communication in 1960. Subsequently, he worked in advertising as a researcher, and in 1968 became vice president and associate director of research at the Foote, Cone and Belding agency in New York. Barrow became the dean of Howard University's School of Communications in 1975, where he worked until 1985. He married his wife, Frederica, in 1992; the couple eventually settled in Florida.
Along with his academic interests, Barrow was an active member of the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication, and was a principle force in helping the organization begin to promote diversity in the field. He founded the Ad Hoc Committee on Minority Education in 1968, and expanded to also form the Minorities and Communication Division in 1970. An AEJMC scholarship was created in his honor to assist women and minorities in their graduate journalism education.
Barrow was also active in politics, fundraising and campaigning for Democratic candidates as early as the 1960s and as recently as the Barack Obama presidential campaign in 2008. He died shortly after Obama's inauguration in January 2009.
Collection Overview
The collection includes materials from Barrow's advertising career, his teaching and tenure at Howard University, and his involvement in the Association for Education in Journalism and Mass Communication (AEJMC). AEJMC materials include a series of folders from a diversity survey in 2004; files from the founding and the operations of the Minorities and Communications Division; and programs and reports from AEJMC activities, especially in the 1970s and 1980s. Materials also reflect Barrow's involvement in the Council for Opportunities in Education, in particular his promotion of the TRIO program, offering funding and education opportunities for underprivileged youth.
A small part of the collection is Barrow's educational materials, dated 1940s-1970s, including reports and essays from his years at Morehouse College as well as his Ph.D. proposals and notes from the University of Wisconsin.
Also included are materials from his service in the 24th Infantry Regiment during the Korean War. The Korean War material, dated 1950-1951, includes press releases, written by Barrow, regarding various battles and army movements. Also included is correspondence to his mother, Wilhelmina Barrow, discussing his activities, as well as his struggles with payment and segregation in the U.S. Army.
Another significant portion of the collection is Barrow's newspaper clippings, dating largely from the 1960s-2000s, covering racial integration and the Civil Rights movement in Washington D.C., issues in journalism, and diversity and the condition of black Americans. These clippings have been loosely arranged by Barrow according to the date, the person's name, or the subject.
There are also numerous folders with clippings and research from Barrow's unfinished book on the history of the Freedom's Journal, the first African-American owned and operated newspaper in the United States. Subjects include slavery, education, conditions in different states, and other information about American life in the 1820s.
Also included are numerous photographs, some dating as early as the 1950s, but the bulk of which date from 1982 to the 2000s. The majority of the photographs snapshots, many featuring the Barrow family. Perhaps more significant are the photographs of professional events with AEJMC, the National Association of Black Journalists, and other conferences and organizations. The photographs have not been arranged, but arrived well-labeled by Barrow, frequently with dates and captions for each image. These materials require more processing before use.
The collection also includes materials from Wilhelmina Barrow, Lionel's mother, relating to her service in the American Red Cross during World War II and in the post-war period. Wilhelmina's materials include ARC training and recruitment documents, her transport papers, newspapers and other publications geared toward servicemen and women, reports from Red Cross Clubs, suggested itineraries for traveling Europe while on leave, and souvenirs from her trips to Italy, France, and Belgium. Also included in this section are reports and clippings about the National Council of Negro Women; Barrow was a member for some time during the 1950s and 1960s. Some of these materials relate to segregation and discrimination.
Acquired as part of the John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture.
Subject Headings
Barrow, Lionel C., 1926-2009; Howard University. School of Communications; Association for Journalism and Mass Communication; Association for Journalism and Mass Communication. Minorities and Communication Division; National Association of Black Journalists; American Red Cross; National Council of Negro Women; United States. Army. Infantry Regiment, 24th -- History; Minorities in journalism; Minorities and journalism; Journalism -- Education; African Americans in the mass media industry; World War, 1939-1945 -- War work -- Red Cross; World War, 1939-1945 -- Women -- African Americans; Washington (D.C.); Clippings; Photographs; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Contents of Collection
- Accession (2010-0031), (12 boxes)
  Most materials have not been sorted or arranged beyond their original condition. Photographs require additional processing before use.
  - AEJMC materials (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Minority Education, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
    - Summer programs, 1970-1988 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Founding of the division, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - Alumni, 1972-1987 (Box 1)
    - Paper on minority division, 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - Journalism Leadership Institute for Diversity (JLID), 1988-1989 (Box 1)
    - NYU summer internship program, 1989-1990 (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Affirmative action, 2000-2001 (Box 1)
    - Minority women article correspondence, 2000s (Box 1)
    - Speech and conference participation, 1992 (Box 1)
    - Contacts to make, 1998-2001 (Box 1)
  - Diversity information, 2004
    - Asian American Journalism Association (Box 1)
    - Accrediting Council on Education JMC (Box 1)
    - American Council on Education (Box 1)
    - Asian and Pacific Island American Scholarship Foundation (ASIASF) (Box 1)
    - American Indian Graduate Center (Box 1)
    - American Association of Advertising Agencies (AAAA) (Box 1)
    - ASJMC (Box 1)
    - ASPIRA (Box 1)
    - Association for Women in Communications (Box 1)
    - California Chicano News Media Association (CCNMA) (Box 1)
    - Chela Education financing (Box 1)
    - Organization of Chinese Americans (Box 1)
    - Corps for National and Community Service (Box 1)
    - Consortium for a Strong Minority Presence (Box 1)
    - Crazy Horse Memorial Foundation (Box 1)
    - Dow Jones Newspaper Fund (Box 1)
    - Freedom Forum (Box 1)
    - Gates Millennium Scholars (Box 1)
    - Hispanic College Fund (Box 1)
    - Hispanic Scholarship Fund (Box 1)
    - Kaiser Family Foundation (Box 1)
    - Knight Foundation (Box 1)
    - La Grant Foundation (Box 1)
    - Lumina Foundation (Box 1)
    - Lin TV (Box 1)
    - National Association of Broadcasting (Box 1)
    - National Association of Hispanic Journalists (Box 1)
    - National Association of Black Journalists (Box 1)
    - National Endowment for the Humanities (Box 1)
    - National Press Club (Box 1)
    - National Science Foundation (2 folders) (Box 1)
    - Newspaper Association of America (Box 1)
    - Native American Journalist Association (Box 1)
    - Public Relations Society of America (Box 1)
    - Poynter Institute (Box 1)
    - Puerto Rico-Virgin Islands (Box 1)
    - Prime Movers Project (Box 1)
    - RTNDF (Box 1)
    - Scripps Howard Foundation (Box 1)
    - Southern Newspaper Press Association (Box 1)
    - Southern California University (Box 1)
    - Training for Journalists (Box 1)
    - Task Force Notes (Box 1)
    - Council for Opportunity in Education (Box 1)
  - National Council of Negro Women, 1950s (Box 1)
  - Clippings
    - Education (Box 1)
    - Black culture (Box 1)
  - Clippings (Box 2)
    - Ebony (Box 2)
    - Magazines about integration (2 folders) (Box 2)
    - Integration (Box 2)
    - Whitney Young/JET (Box 2)
    - Martin Luther King, Jr. (Box 2)
    - Psychology and sociology, 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
  - Wilhelmina Browne Barrow materials, 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
  - Wilhelmina Barrow UN publications and other materials, 1950s-1960s (Box 2)
  - Awards, 1944-1997 (Box 2)
  - Plaques (3) (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1990-1995 and undated (Box 2)
  - Advertising classes: teaching notes, syllabi, research, etc. (24 folders) (Box 3)
  - Clippings/publications about advertising and advertisements, 1990s (Box 3)
  - Books
    - Media Planning (Box 3)
    - Making Advertisements (Box 3)
    - Current Issues and Research in Advertising (Box 3)
    - Advertising Theory and Practice (Box 3)
    - Advertising Research (Box 3)
  - Clippings, 1960s (Box 4)
    - George Wallace (Box 4)
    - Washington, D.C. (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Government and politics (Box 4)
    - Riots (Box 4)
    - Education (Box 4)
    - Poverty (Box 4)
    - Women's rights (Box 4)
    - Community news and miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Race Relations Reporter issues, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Segregation and integration printed materials, 1950s-1960s (Box 4)
  - Wilhelmina Barrow's printed materials, 1940s-1960s (Box 4)
  - O. Grady Review notes (Box 4)
  - Notes and research, 1968 (Box 4)
  - Marx articles (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1960s-1970s (Box 4)
  - Wilhelmina Barrow notes and correspondence, undated (Box 4)
  - Advertising courses and teaching materials
    - Language-Black English (Box 4)
    - Minorities and media lectures (Box 4)
    - What is Blackness? (Box 4)
    - Lectures, current (2 folders) (Box 4)
    - Introduction to mass media (6 folders) (Box 4)
    - Role of mass communication (Box 4)
    - Black males in media (Box 4)
    - Blacks in broadcasting (3 folders) (Box 4)
    - Negro market study (Box 4)
    - Racism in language (Box 4)
  - Advertising courses and teaching materials (Box 5)
    - Communication media analyses (Box 5)
    - History of the black press (Box 5)
    - Janet Cooke clippings (Box 5)
    - Urban Crisis clippings (Box 5)
    - Minorities and communication (Box 5)
  - AEJMC conferences, materials, papers, 1968-1977 (11 folders) (Box 5)
  - AEJMC Minorities and Communication Division (MAC), 1970-2001 (7 folders) (Box 5)
  - MAC newsletters, 1970-2002 (Box 5)
  - MAC annual reports, 1971-2001 (5 folders) (Box 5)
  - AEJMC official convention reports, 1969-1981 (Box 5)
  - AEJMC standing committee reports, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
  - AEJMC newsletters, 1974-2002 (2 folders) (Box 5)
  - AEJMC Theory and Methodology Division (Box 5)
  - Diversity studies and reports, AEJMC and others, 1970-2002 (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - AEJMC Barrow Communication Theory and Methodology Division (CT&M) Scholarship, 1980-2002 (4 folders) (Box 6)
  - Other AEJMC divisions' diversity efforts, 1966-2002 (6 folders) (Box 6)
  - Teaching, research, course materials
    - Population and occupation statistics (Box 6)
    - Negro women (Box 6)
    - Reconstruction (Box 6)
    - Slavery and reconstruction (Box 6)
    - Black business (3 folders) (Box 6)
    - How we spend our money (2 folders) (Box 6)
    - Collective change (Box 6)
    - History, general (7 folders) (Box 6)
  - Minority telecommunications developments (Box 6)
  - Economics of the Black community (3 folders) (Box 6)
  - Minority employment (Box 6)
  - Minority community education (Box 6)
  - Role of minority women article (Box 6)
  - The Star newspapers, 1949-1950 (Box 6)
  - Directory of women and minority men in academic journalism, 1973-1975 (Box 6)
  - Photographs, 1992-2000 (includes Frederica and Lionel's wedding, 1992) (Box 7)
  - Photographs, 1973-1987 (bulk 1981-1983) (Box 8)
  - Photographs, 1982-1989 (Box 9)
  - Morehouse College correspondence, 2004 (Box 9)
  - National Association of Black Journalists (Box 9)
  - Task Force on Diversity, 2005 (Box 9)
  - Council for Opportunity in Education (COE) (Box 9)
  - AEJMC MAC Division beginning (Box 9)
  - AEJMC MAC (Box 9)
  - AEJMC CSM newsletter (Box 9)
  - AEJMC CT&M Division (Box 9)
  - Obama election, 2007-2008 (11 folders) (Box 9)
  - Council for Opportunity in Education (COE) TRIO programs, 1995-2002 (12 folders) (Box 9)
  - 2 COE videotapes (Box 9)
  - Articles and publicity about journalism profession (Box 9)
  - Oversize photographs, 2008 and undated (Box 10)
  - Photographs, 1983-1984 (Box 10)
  - Photograph album, 1983-1984 (including National Association of Black Journalists) (Box 10)
  - Barrow's personal correspondence, other papers, 1970s (Box 10)
  - Barrow's ticket stub album, 1970s-1980s (Box 10)
  - Stamp collecting materials (Box 10)
  - America's Black Forum, 1978 (Box 10)
  - Journalism code of ethics materials, 1970s-1990s (16 folders) (Box 10)
  - Journalism code of ethics materials (6 folders) (Box 11)
  - Photographs, 2000s (Box 11)
  - Photographs (Box 12)
    - 5 albums, 1960s-2000s (Box 12)
    - 15 mini albums, including some labelled famous folks (Box 12)
    - Loose photographs, 1960s-2000s (Box 12)
    - Some oversize materials, including Focus Advertising materials and oversize stamp collecting materials (Box 12)
- Accession (2010-0079), 1940-2000s, (15 boxes)
  - Name and Subject clippings/files re: minorities, diversity, and racism, 1990s-2000s (Box 13)
    - Americana (2 files) (Box 13)
    - Diversity (Box 13)
    - Sept. 11, 2001 (Box 13)
    - International (Box 13)
    - Maryland (Box 13)
    - Science (Box 13)
    - Charles Shultz (Box 13)
    - Shakespeare (Box 13)
    - Middle East (Box 13)
    - Afro-centric/Multicultural education (Box 13)
    - Cultural differences (Box 13)
    - FBI and minorities (Box 13)
    - FCC (Box 13)
    - Famous folks (Box 13)
    - Attorneys, Black (Box 13)
    - Afro-American inventors (Box 13)
    - Marion Anderson (Box 13)
    - Arthur Ashe (Box 13)
    - James Baldwin (Box 13)
    - Marion Barry (Box 13)
    - H. Rap Brown (Box 13)
    - Stokely Carmichael (Box 13)
    - Shirley Chisholm (Box 13)
    - Ken Clarke and Ann Sealy Clarke (Box 13)
    - Billy Eckstine (Box 13)
    - Ralph Ellison (Box 13)
    - Newt Gingrich (Box 13)
    - Ben Hooks (Box 13)
    - Jesse Jackson (Box 13)
    - Barbara Jordan (Box 13)
    - Vernon Jordan (Box 13)
    - M.L. King (Box 13)
    - Malcolm X (Box 13)
    - Nelson Mandela/South Africa (Box 13)
    - Thurgood Marshall (2 folders) (Box 13)
    - Black Panthers (Box 13)
    - Adam Clayton Powell, Jr. (3 folders) (Box 13)
    - Rosa Parks (Box 13)
    - Black Politics (Box 13)
    - Colin Powell (Box 13)
    - FDR (Box 13)
    - Jackie Robinson (Box 13)
    - Eleanor Roosevelt (Box 13)
    - OJ Simpson (Box 13)
    - Lillian Smith (Box 13)
    - Clarence Thomas (Box 13)
    - Madam CJ Walker (Box 13)
    - Eddie Wons (Box 13)
    - Alice Walker (Box 13)
    - Vanessa Williams (Box 13)
    - Tiger Woods (Box 13)
    - Public broadcasting (Box 13)
    - UDC (Box 13)
    - Affirmative action (Box 13)
    - WEB Dubois (Box 13)
    - Mid-East/Andy Young (Box 13)
  - Name and Subject clippings/files (Box 14)
    - Mervin Aubespin (Box 14)
    - Harry Belafonte (Box 14)
    - Lerone Bennett Jr. (Box 14)
    - Black Collegian (Box 14)
    - Black Journal (TV series) (Box 14)
    - Ray Boone (Box 14)
    - Burrell Ad Agency (Box 14)
    - Earl Caldwell case, 1972 (Box 14)
    - Charlie Cobb (Box 14)
    - Bill Cosby (Box 14)
    - Ossie Davis (Box 14)
    - Summary of other pertinent literature (Freedom's Journal research) (Box 14)
    - Research methods course (Box 14)
    - Evaluation criteria/procedure (Box 14)
    - Algebra I (Box 14)
    - Children's programming research (Box 14)
    - Advanced statistics (Box 14)
    - Covariance analysis (Box 14)
    - Experimental research in communications (Box 14)
    - Theory (2 folders) (Box 14)
    - Correlation (Box 14)
    - Regression analysis (Box 14)
    - Statistics procedures (Box 14)
    - Contingency tables (Box 14)
    - Chi squares (Box 14)
    - Factor analysis (Box 14)
    - Processes (Box 14)
    - Mass communications (Box 14)
    - Disc. of statistical power (Box 14)
    - Range tests (Box 14)
    - Intermedia Comparisons Conference, 1983 (Box 14)
    - Profile-matching media relations (Box 14)
    - Experimental design (Box 14)
    - Experimental research course (Box 14)
    - Factor-regression studies (Box 14)
  - Name and Subject clippings/files (Box 15)
    - Frederick Douglass and the North Star (5 folders) (Box 15)
    - Robert Johnson-JET (Box 15)
    - Bertram Lee (Box 15)
    - Spike Lee (Box 15)
    - Media in Africa (Box 15)
    - Black-white intermarriage (Box 15)
    - Ohio, Blacks in (Box 15)
    - Kenneth Jennings, 1992 (Box 15)
    - Forrester B. Washington (Box 15)
  - Business files
    - MLK breakfast, 1999 (Box 15)
    - Possible client: Major R. Owens (Box 15)
    - Possible client: The Afro-American (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, 1985-1992 (Box 15)
    - Job search, 1986 (Box 15)
    - Personal, 1986 (Box 15)
    - International Curriculum Development Conference, 1981 (Box 15)
    - Loans (Box 15)
    - Who's Who (Box 15)
    - National Press Club (Box 15)
    - Black Business Council (Box 15)
    - Chase Manhattan (Box 15)
    - American Association of Colleges for Teacher's Education (Box 15)
    - American Visions questionnaire (Box 15)
    - American Society of Newspaper Editors (ASNE) (Box 15)
    - Athlete-Career Connections (Arthur Ashe) (Box 15)
    - Afro-American, Cultural, Technological, and Scientific Olympics (ACT-SO) (Box 15)
    - NC Mutual Centennial Program (Box 15)
    - CANA (Box 15)
    - Crisis Magazine (2 folders) (Box 15)
    - East-West Center proposal (Box 15)
    - Freedom Forum (Box 15)
    - Haley, George (Box 15)
    - Hayes, Terrence (Box 15)
    - Hutt, Lou and Kevin (Box 15)
    - Intercultural Communication (Box 15)
    - INAME Foundation (Box 15)
    - Matthews, Dan (Box 15)
    - Montgomery Times (Box 15)
    - Washington Association of Black Journalists (Box 15)
    - National Association of Educational Broadcasters, 1975 (Box 15)
    - National Newspaper Publishing Assocation (NNPA) (Box 15)
    - NTIA-Thomas Hardy (Box 15)
    - Parity Press, Inc. (Box 15)
    - Peabody Awards (Box 15)
    - Pyramid Books (Box 15)
    - Humphries, Derrick (Box 15)
    - Tom Skinner Association (Box 15)
    - Slater, Bill (Box 15)
    - Social Security Administration (SSI) Project (Box 15)
    - Tanque, Marcus (Box 15)
    - UMC Global Ministries (Box 15)
    - Wallace, Arnold (New Breed Media Group) (Box 15)
    - Walls, Lon (Box 15)
    - Wright, Ben (Box 15)
    - Universities, correspondence (28 folders) (Box 15)
    - City of Baltimore (Box 15)
  - Name and Subject clippings/files (Box 16)
    - Bill Cosby tirade (Box 16)
    - Prior research: Blacks in the 18th century (Box 16)
    - Aptheker-History/Black Press (Box 16)
    - War correspondents, Black (Box 16)
    - Media/censorship (Box 16)
    - History clippings (Box 16)
    - Columbia College, Chicago (Box 16)
    - ID theft (Box 16)
    - Local School Board, Brooklyn (Barrows was a member) (Box 16)
    - Franz Fanon (Box 16)
    - Stepin Fetchit (Box 16)
    - Carl Franklin (Box 16)
    - Marcus Garvey (Box 16)
    - H. Germina (Box 16)
    - Mal Goode (Box 16)
    - Danny Glover (Box 16)
    - Earl Graves (Box 16)
    - Bryant Gumbel (Box 16)
    - Arsenio Hall (Box 16)
    - Alex Haley (Box 16)
    - Hudlin Brothers (Box 16)
    - John H. Johnson (Box 16)
    - Robert Johnson, BET (Box 16)
    - Communications, 1988 (Box 16)
    - Media and Blacks (Box 16)
    - Media, 1970s (Box 16)
    - Changing white media (Box 16)
    - Media-other minorities (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
    - Cancer Center (Howard University) (6 folders) (Box 16)
  - Freedom's Journal research (13 folders) (Box 16)
  - Freedom's Journal research, geography (19 folders) (Box 17)
    - Impact (Box 17)
    - Association for the Study of African American Life and History (6 folders) (Box 17)
    - Woodson, Carter G. (Box 17)
  - Name and Subject clippings/files
    - Racism (Box 17)
    - Religion (Box 17)
    - Public broadcasting (Box 17)
    - Travel (Box 17)
    - NAOEB (Box 17)
    - Minority TV producers (Box 17)
    - Communications, general (Box 17)
    - Sources of materials for teaching course on Blacks and the Media (Box 17)
    - Broadcasting (4 folders) (Box 17)
    - Broadcasting (9 folders) (Box 18)
    - Film (35 folders) (Box 18)
    - NATRA-Record Industry (Box 18)
    - Local mass communication agencies (Box 18)
  - Freedom's Journal research (13 folders) (Box 18)
  - Freedom's Journal research (39 folders) (Box 19)
  - Cassette tapes (27), including recordings of NABJ, AEJ, Congressional Black Caucus, NBMC, and interviews, 1980s-1990s (Box 19)
  - Freedom's Journal research (Box 20)
    - Black press (Box 20)
    - Special topics (Box 20)
    - Black media (Box 20)
    - Media today (Box 20)
  - Name and Subject clippings/files (Box 21)